<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The genealogie and pedigree of the most illustrious and most mighty kings in Sueden. Collected out of sundry writers of histories from the yeare 1250, vnto this present time, produced and published. By Andrevv Hildebrandt, Doctor in Physicke, and physitian for the body to the Duke of Pomeren. First, printed in Stettin, in High-Dutch, by Nicholas Barthold, anno, 1631. And translated into English, by Sr. S.L. Knight</title>
            <title>Genealogia regum Sueciae. English</title>
            <author>Hildebrandt, Andreas, d. 1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122413</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857562</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857562</idno>
            <idno type="VID">23319</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03338)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 23319)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 962:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The genealogie and pedigree of the most illustrious and most mighty kings in Sueden. Collected out of sundry writers of histories from the yeare 1250, vnto this present time, produced and published. By Andrevv Hildebrandt, Doctor in Physicke, and physitian for the body to the Duke of Pomeren. First, printed in Stettin, in High-Dutch, by Nicholas Barthold, anno, 1631. And translated into English, by Sr. S.L. Knight</title>
                  <title>Genealogia regum Sueciae. English</title>
                  <author>Hildebrandt, Andreas, d. 1637.</author>
                  <author>L., S., Sir, fl. 1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Beale] for Iames Boler, at the Marigold in Pauls-Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Probably a translation of a German translation of: Genealogia regum Sueciae.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ (A2 + a² ) B-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued separately as part of: A short survey or history of the kingdome of Sueden.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sweden --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sweden --  Kings and rulers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="genealogy">
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE GENEALOGIE OR PEDEGREE OF THE MOST ILLVSTRIOVS AND MOST MIGH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TY KINGS OF <hi>SVEDEN.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>NGE MVNDVS WAS A ſurnamed <hi>Trolle,</hi> Knight, did live about the yeer of Chriſt 1250.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholaus</hi> the firſt Knight and Councellor of the kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1285.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtiernus</hi> the firſt Knight, and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour
<pb facs="tcp:23319:2"/>(under King <hi>Birgerius</hi>) in <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holme,</hi> the chiefe City in <hi>Sweden, Anno.</hi> 1290.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christiernus</hi> 2. Knight, and Eſquire to the kingdome of <hi>Sweden.</hi> 1301.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> 1. Eſquire to the kingdome of Sweden.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Catillus</hi> 1. Eſquire to the kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> hee lived in the yeare of Chriſt, 1330.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His Wife was</hi> Chriſtina, <hi>the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:23319:2"/>of</hi> Bononis-Iohannis, <hi>Knight, hee had iſſue by her,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas</hi> 2. Of the Familie <hi>Fort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plantzer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> 2. Eſquire to the kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> and Father to <hi>Charles</hi> 3. Knight, and Councellor to the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Sweden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nicholas</hi> 2. of <hi>Biorno,</hi> Knight, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour in <hi>Stockholme,</hi> vnder King <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1360.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>His wife was</hi> Chriſtina, <hi>the daughter of</hi> Iohn Nicholas <hi>of</hi> Guldenſtern, <hi>alſo a Knight, and Councellor of the kingdome of</hi> Sweden, <hi>and had iſſue by her,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:23319:3"/> 1 <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> 3. Of the family <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rern.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Caecilia,</hi> which was married to <hi>Thore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Bendenum</hi> Governour in <hi>Wiburg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 <hi>Ingeburgim,</hi> which was a Nunne in the Cloyſter of S. <hi>Clara</hi> in <hi>Stockhollme.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtiern.</hi> 3. Chiefe Councellour, and Arch-Sewen of the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden,</hi> dyed in the yeare of Chriſt, 1442. His wife was <hi>Margaret,</hi> a daughter of <hi>Eric Krumdick</hi> of <hi>Tranecker,</hi> Knight, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of the kingdome, who dyed 1451, they had iſſue together,
<list>
                  <item>1. <hi>John.</hi> 1. The Increaſer of the Kings race.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Charles</hi> 4. of whom more men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be made by and by.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Nicholas</hi> 3. Baron of <hi>Diurſholm,</hi> Knight, and Commander in <hi>We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraſien</hi> and <hi>Dalecarlien<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Hee dyed 1462.</item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Christina,</hi> who was married to <hi>Benedict Iohn,</hi> the Kings chiefe Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
<pb facs="tcp:23319:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>in <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pland;</hi> She was mother to
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Iohn,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Vpſalia.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Chriſtiern,</hi> Lord of <hi>Saleſtadt.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Charles</hi> 4. Knight and Councellor of <hi>Sweden,</hi> dyed at Revell before his father, <hi>Anno</hi> 1440. Hee had iſſue with <hi>Ebba</hi> of <hi>Krumdick,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Catillus</hi> 2. Biſhop in <hi>Lincopin,</hi> who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the plague 1465.</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Eric</hi> of <hi>Norby,</hi> Knight and Councellor to the kingdome of <hi>Sweden.</hi> His wife was <hi>Anna,</hi> daughter of <hi>Charls Benedict</hi> of <hi>Winſetory,</hi> knight alſo, and Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor to the kingdome; who the ſecond time married and took to wife <hi>Erichen</hi> of <hi>Guldenſtern;</hi> their firſt daughter was</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ebba,</hi> who was married to <hi>Erichen</hi> of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolm,</hi> Knight, and Preſident of <hi>Weſt-goth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Abraham</hi> of <hi>Eckberg.</hi> This man was beheaded in <hi>Holm,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1520 by commandement of <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> 2. King
<pb facs="tcp:23319:4"/>in <hi>Denmarke;</hi> Shee died, 1549. Shee had iſſue, amongſt other children,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Margaret,</hi> which was the ſecond wife to <hi>Guſtavus</hi> the firſt of this line, King of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andales,</hi> &amp;c. Shee depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this life, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 26. 1551.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Oreby,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> 3 Knight and Councellor of the kingdom of Sweden, departed out of this world vpon Eaſter day, in the yeere of Chriſt, 1477. He had to wife, <hi>Bridget;</hi> a daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Guſtavus Sture,</hi> and <hi>Bridget Turon,</hi> who was a ſiſter of <hi>Steno Sture,</hi> the elder of <hi>Gripſolme,</hi> and Governour of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Sweden.</p>
               <p>The foreſaid <hi>Bridget</hi> died in <hi>Anno,</hi> 1472. and had iſſue by her ſaid husband, <hi>Ericus</hi> 1. Of the line of <hi>Fortsflanter. Chriſtiern</hi> 4. Of <hi>Oreby,</hi> Knight. <hi>Anna,</hi> wife of <hi>Iohn Turo,</hi> Marſhall
<pb facs="tcp:23319:4"/>of the kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ericus</hi> 1. of <hi>Gripſolm,</hi> Knight, and Councellour to the kingdome of Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Governour of <hi>Eland,</hi> &amp;c. He was by <hi>Christiern</hi> 2. King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the Market-place, at <hi>Holm,</hi> in <hi>Anno Chriſti,</hi> 1520, the 8 of November. His wife was <hi>Caecilia,</hi> a daughter of <hi>Magnus Charles</hi> of <hi>Eka,</hi> Knight and Councellour of the kingdome of Sweden. Shee was alſo, together with other Ladies and yong Gentlewomen, caſt into priſon by the ſaid King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> and ſhortly after carried into <hi>Denmarke,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1520, having before brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world,
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Guſtavus</hi> of the line of <hi>Vermehren.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Marg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>et,</hi> firſt married to <hi>Peter Brahe,</hi> Earle of <hi>Wiſingsburg,</hi> and Baron of <hi>Rib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deholm.</hi> Shee was married after to <hi>Iohn,</hi> Earle of <hi>Hoien,</hi> who was ſlaine in a
<pb facs="tcp:23319:5"/>battell that happened at <hi>Ochſenbring,</hi> in <hi>Finland</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt 1534, the 11 of <hi>Iune.</hi> He was the father of <hi>Iohn,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Munster,</hi> and <hi>Osnabruck,</hi> who died, <hi>Anno</hi> 1574.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Magnus</hi> 1.</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Iohn</hi> 2</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Bridget.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6 <hi>Anna,</hi> who died in the yeare 1514.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guſtavus,</hi> a Knight of <hi>Sweden,</hi> was borne in the yeare of Chriſt, 1490: he had his education from his youth in the Court of <hi>Steno Sture</hi> his Grandmothers brother: hee ſhewed his firſt Act of valour under <hi>Suanto,</hi> Marſhall of the ſaid kingdome, and was mad chiefe Cornet of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volarie vnder the command of <hi>Steno</hi> the younger, where hee behaved himſelfe ſo well in two ſeverall Battels, in which
<pb facs="tcp:23319:5"/>
                  <hi>Steno</hi> had the victory, that his valour was highly commended: hee was after wards, and his Conſorts, being deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded hoſtages by <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> 2. King in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> carried Priſoners into <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> and ſo kept in a Caſtle called <hi>Kalp,</hi> in <hi>Iutland;</hi> out of which, hee not long after, in a diſguiſed habit, being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne, eſcaped and arrived ſafe at <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1519; from thence paſſing through many dangers, arrived, in the end, ſafely in his owne Countrey <hi>Sweden,</hi> and came into <hi>Reffnas,</hi> his Couſins pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimony. But when hee underſtood that his Father, with others principall States of the kingdome were lately before ſtrangely put to death, he was ſo incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt the enemies of his native Country, that he did aſſemble together his Countrey-men from all places, to whom hee repreſented the miſerable eſtate of their native Country, and that they were all dead men, if they did not free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the preſent tyranny by ioynt
<pb facs="tcp:23319:6"/>ayd and aſſiſtance. Whereupon hee was inſtantly choſen, by the Sates of <hi>Dalien,</hi> Governour, named and proclaimed to be the Protectour of the liberties in the yeare of Chriſt, 1521. Hee had out of <hi>Darlecarlien</hi> a brave Companie of men, which are accounted the valianteſt men in the whole kingdome of Sweden, with whom he did purſue the <hi>Danes</hi> who had enquartered themſelves in <hi>Scandia,</hi> and did beſiege <hi>Holm</hi> for the ſpace of two yeares, which is the chiefe City in the kingdome, and in the end took the ſame, and by the helpe of the valiant Towneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, did beate out the <hi>Danes</hi> that were there in Garriſon. For this heroicall fact he was choſen King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Goth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the fourth of <hi>Iune,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1523, and named a Deliuerer of the Native Countrey, with much ioy and alacrity by all that did truly loue their Countrey.</p>
               <p>This being done, he did firſt of all (to the end hee might manifeſt his thankfull diſpoſition, and that he was not vnmind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:23319:6"/>of the kinde deeds expreſſed towards him) ratifie and confirme in his owne and the States name of Sweden to the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of <hi>Lubeck, Dantzick,</hi> and to other neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Cities, ſtately and great privileges, rights and immunities granted vnto them. Hee did not receive the Crowne till the 12. of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> 1528, after ſuch time as hee had cauſed all thoſe to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted who might have beene an hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vnto him, and who through the <q>Biſhops power, and abundance of riches, were growne ſtubborne, who did raiſe one diſquietneſſe vpon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the Kings,</q> and who were alſo the onely occaſion of all the former warres and inſurrections.</p>
               <p>Now the civill and forraigne warres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus happily brought to an end, and the wiſhed peace appearing againe, to the end that the kingdome which was thus recovered by meanes of his heroicall vertues and valour might bee ſo maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, he tooke ſpecial care that good lawes
<pb facs="tcp:23319:7"/>and diſcipline with the exerciſe of the true Religion, ſhould be ſetled and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed throughout the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And thus hee continued and reigned peaceably the ſpace of 40 yeares, untill his death, which happened the 29 of <hi>November,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1560, at the age of 70 yeares, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſalia,</hi> He had three wives, the firſt, <hi>Katharine,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Magnus</hi> 2. Duke of <hi>Low-Saxony</hi> in <hi>Engern</hi> and <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phalia,</hi> they was married at <hi>Stockholm</hi> the 24 of September, 1531. Shee had, foure yeares after, a fall from her horſe, whereof ſhee died the 23 of September, 1535.</p>
               <p>The ſecond was <hi>Margaret</hi> his Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman, the daughter of <hi>Eric Abraham</hi> of <hi>Loholm,</hi> Knight, and Governour of <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothland.</hi> This <hi>Eric Abraham</hi> was alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed in <hi>Anno</hi> 1520, by the command of <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> 2. King of <hi>Denmarke:</hi> he did marry her the firſt of October, 1536, in which yeare ſhe was alſo crowned. This <hi>Margaret</hi> dyed the 26 of Auguſt, 1551.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:23319:7"/>
               <p> The third wife was <hi>Katherine,</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> Governour in Weſt <hi>Goth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with whom he was married in <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein</hi> 1552 (<hi>Chytr. lib.</hi> 17. <hi>Saxon.</hi>) Hee had iſſue by theſe three wives ſix ſonnes, and three daughters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>With the firſt.</head>
               <p>☞</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ericke,</hi> ſecond King of the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Goths,</hi> of his name the XIIII. was borne the 13. of <hi>December</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1533. He was choſen King in the aſſembly of his own and forraigne Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Ambaſſadours the 24 <hi>Iune</hi> 1561. He had war 7 yeeres together with <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> the 2 King of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> which in the <q>end, namely in <hi>Anno</hi> 1570. was happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compoſed &amp; agreed upon in <hi>Stetin</hi> in <hi>Pomeren,</hi> where were preſent Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors &amp; Commiſſioners from <hi>Maximilian</hi> the 2 <hi>Roman</hi> Emperor, from <hi>Charles</hi> the 9. King of <hi>France,</hi> from <hi>Sigiſmund Auguſt</hi> King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Elector
<pb facs="tcp:23319:8"/>of <hi>Saxe,</hi> and from other Princes. Alſo thoſe of <hi>Stetin</hi> obtained this privilege. That for all the goods in a ſhip, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Sound, they ſhould pay for ſhip and all for cuſtome, no more than one Roſe-noble.</q> At the beginning of theſe warres, this <hi>Eric</hi> cauſed his Brother <hi>Iohn,</hi> Duke of <hi>Finland</hi> to be apprehended in the night, and committed Priſoner in the Caſtle <hi>Aboen</hi> at that time when the ſaid <hi>John</hi> leaſt thought of it; <hi>Eric</hi> having no other cauſe than a ſuſpition which he had of him that he was not to be truſted becauſe the ſaid <hi>Iohn</hi> his wife, who was ſiſter to <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> King of <hi>Polonia</hi> was his enemie, and made all his neighbours to riſe againſt him. Having thus held <hi>Iohn</hi> ſundry yeares in Priſon, with his ſonne, a childe of two yeares old, in the end hee purpoſed to put them both to death, that hee might afterwards give his brothers wife in marriage to the <hi>Muſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit,</hi> whereunto they two were before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed. But before that hee could accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh
<pb facs="tcp:23319:8"/>that purpoſe of his, hee became di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted in his ſenſes, whereat the whole kingdome was much troubled, and his Brother <hi>Iohn</hi> obtained his liberty againe, who held <hi>Eric</hi> Priſoner in <hi>Orbey,</hi> and ſo the chance was turned; All which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the yeare of Chriſt, 1568. <hi>Eric</hi> dyed in Priſon, in the yeare 1578, and was buried in <hi>Weſtraſia</hi> in <hi>Finland.</hi> Hee had iſſue from <hi>Katharine</hi> his Concubine, a woman of meane parentage, whom at laſt, as ſome report, hee did marry the 4 of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1568.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Guſtavus</hi> a Baſtard who was ſent for unto <hi>Moschkaw</hi> by <hi>Boride Fedrowitz,</hi> to the end hee ſhould marrie his daughter, but hee returned home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine without her. He lived a while at <hi>Prague</hi> in the Court of <hi>Rodulph</hi> the ſecond Emperour, (whereof M. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel Adamus</hi> of <hi>Mulaſlaw</hi> in his <hi>Bohemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> hyſtoricall Kalender,) ſome write that hee dyed in <hi>Aulitz,</hi> in <hi>Muſcovia,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:23319:9"/>in the yeere 1607.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Syria,</hi> who was married unto <hi>Henry Tadden</hi> Baron in <hi>Finlandt.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>With the ſecond.</head>
               <p>☞</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the third King of <hi>Sweden</hi> and of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> Duke of <hi>Finland,</hi> &amp;c. was borne in <hi>Steckburge</hi> in the Province of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrogoth</hi> 1537, the 21 of <hi>December.</hi> After that his brother <hi>Erick,</hi> by Gods iuſt iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was growne out of his ſenſes; this <hi>Iohn,</hi> together with his wife and his Son, were delivered out of their impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 28. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1568. and was crowned King the 13. of <hi>October</hi> following: and conſidering that his brother <hi>Erick</hi> would not give eare, nor follow any good advice, nor admit any friendly treaty, <hi>Iohn,</hi> with the generall conſent and aſſiſtance of the whole States and Commons in the Kingdome, beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb facs="tcp:23319:9"/>him in <hi>Stockholm;</hi> the reaſon there of was then made knowne to all men by publike Proclamation, and thereupon as ſoon as the City of <hi>Stockholm</hi> had yeelded, <hi>Erick</hi> was taken and put into the ſame priſon wherein <hi>Iohn</hi> had beene kept be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Two yeeres after <hi>Iohn</hi> had made a peace with <hi>Frederick</hi> the 2. King in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> which was confirmed and ratified by the interpoſition of the Emperor and other Kings and Princes: hee did alſo in the yeere of Chriſt 1580 conclude a leagu with <hi>Stephon Bathori</hi> King of <hi>Polonia:</hi> the next yeere being 1581, he tooke <hi>Finlandt</hi> from the <hi>Muſcouite,</hi> &amp; ſent a fleet of Ships into <hi>Leiflandt,</hi> tooke the City of <hi>Narue,</hi> and ſlew 5000. <hi>Muſcouites.</hi> This <hi>Iohn</hi> dyed the 17. of <hi>Nouember</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1592. of 55 yeers of age, and was buried in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſalia,</hi> leaving iſſue as followeth: By <hi>Katherine</hi> (the daughter of <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> firſt King in <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Bona Sfortza,</hi> Dutcheſſe of <hi>Milan,</hi> with
<pb facs="tcp:23319:10"/>whom hee was married the 4 of <hi>Octo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> 1562, and ſhee alſo crowned the 10 of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1569. Shee dyed the 16 of <hi>September,</hi> 1593, and was the next bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried by her Husband in <hi>Vpſalia;</hi> as wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>Iohn Meſen</hi> in his deſcription of the ancient and following Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Goths.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Their Iſſue.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> 3. of that name, King of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonia,</hi> of whom hereafter more mention ſhall be made under the letter B.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſabella,</hi> horne in the yeare of Chriſt, 1567, dyed in her infancie, and was bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at <hi>Stregniez.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anna Infanta</hi> of <hi>Sweden,</hi> borne at <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chilstan,</hi> the 8 of <hi>May, Anno</hi> 1568. Shee lived, for a time, in the Court of her bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> and dyed in <hi>Stratsburg</hi> in <hi>Pruſſe,</hi> 27 Ianuary, 1615.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:23319:10"/>
               <p> By <hi>Gumilla,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Iohn B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>elki,</hi> Governour in <hi>Oſtrogoth,</hi> a principall Family.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn,</hi> Prince in <hi>Finland</hi> and <hi>Oſtrogoth,</hi> born in <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſalia,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1589, the 18 of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prill. Hee married the 29 of Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, 1612, <hi>Mary Elizabeth,</hi> daughter of <hi>Charls,</hi> King of Sweden, and of the <hi>Goths,</hi> his fathers brothers daughter. He dyed at <hi>VVaſten</hi> where he kept his Court, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1618, and ſhee dyed 1619, and both are buried in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Church of <hi>Lyncopin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Katharine</hi> was borne 6 Iune, in <hi>Anno</hi> 1539 and was married to <hi>Ezard</hi> 2, Earle of <hi>Eaſt Frieſland,</hi> the 1. of October, 1559.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Caecilia</hi> was borne 6 November, 1540. and was married to <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Marquis of <hi>Baden,</hi> in the yeare of Chriſt, 1564.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23319:11"/> 5 <hi>Magnus</hi> Duke of <hi>Eastgothland</hi> Earle; of <hi>Dalien,</hi> was born 25. <hi>Iuly,</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1542 died diſtracted in <hi>Anno</hi> 1595. and is buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Waſten.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Steno</hi> was borne in the yeere of Chriſt 1544. and died in <hi>Anno</hi> 1549. and is buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the chiefe Church of <hi>Lyncopin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7 <hi>Anna</hi> was borne the 9 of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1545. She was married to <hi>George Iohn</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhyne</hi> in <hi>Leitzelſtein</hi> and <hi>Landereck</hi> 18. <hi>October,</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1563. She was amongſt other by <hi>George Guſtaue</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> a Grandmother to <hi>Charles Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uick</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhyne,</hi> &amp;c. born the fift of <hi>February</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1609.</p>
               <p n="8">8 <hi>Charles</hi> the fift was born in <hi>Ann.</hi> 1546. but died preſently after hee was baptized, and was buried at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9 <hi>Sophia</hi> was borne 29. <hi>Octo. Ann.</hi> 1547. and was married unto <hi>Magnus,</hi> Duke in <hi>Lower Saxe,</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Francis</hi> I. the 4. of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1568.</p>
               <p n="10">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23319:11"/> 10 <hi>Elizabeth</hi> was borne in <hi>Anno</hi> 1549. and was married unto <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Mechelburg</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1581. in <hi>Stockholm,</hi> and there ſhe died 19. <hi>Nouember</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1597.</p>
               <p n="11">11 <hi>Charles</hi> the 6 of this family, was born betweene the 4 and 5 of <hi>October</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1550. Duke of <hi>Finland, Sudermania</hi> and <hi>Nericia, &amp;c.</hi> after that he had continued in warres with <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> King of <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Suede</hi> (who was his brothers Nephew) was by the States of the Kingdome ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted King of <hi>Sueden,</hi> of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales,</hi> the 19 of <hi>March</hi> 1600. and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the accuſtomed manner hee was alſo the 15 of <hi>March</hi> 1607. crowned. He died in <hi>Norcopin</hi> the 29 of <hi>October</hi> in <hi>Anno</hi> 1611. of the age of 61 yeeres, and is buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Stregnitz</hi> He had iſſue.</p>
               <p>☞ With <hi>Mary</hi> daughter of <hi>Ludovick</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Elector. She was married to him the 11 of <hi>May</hi> in <hi>An.</hi> 1579. and died 29 <hi>Iuly</hi> 1589. and
<pb facs="tcp:23319:12"/>had iſſue by him</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Margaret Elizabeth,</hi> borne in <hi>Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copin</hi> the 23 <hi>September,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1580. and died the 27 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1585.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Elizabeth Sabina</hi> born 12 of <hi>March,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1582. but died in <hi>Nycopin</hi> the 6 <hi>July</hi> 1585.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Ludouicke</hi> Duke of <hi>Suderman,</hi> &amp;c. was borne in <hi>Heidelberg</hi> 17 <hi>March</hi> in the yeere 1583. but he died few dayes after.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Katherin</hi> was borne in <hi>Nycopin</hi> the 10 or 11 of <hi>Nouember</hi> 1584. and was married the 11 of <hi>Iune,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1615. un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iohn Caſimire</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhyne</hi> in <hi>New Caſtel,</hi> being ſonne unto <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Zweybrucken.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Guſtauus</hi> 2, Duke of <hi>Suderman, &amp;c.</hi> was borne in <hi>Nycopin</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1587 the 12 of <hi>Iune,</hi> &amp; died the 4 of <hi>Decemb.</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb facs="tcp:23319:12"/> 6 <hi>Mary</hi> borne in <hi>Marienholm</hi> the 18. of <hi>December</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1588 and dyed the 24 of <hi>Aprill</hi> 1589.</p>
               <p>☞ With <hi>Christina</hi> the daughter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolph,</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> and neece to <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> the I. King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> &amp;c. married the 27 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1592. they two had iſſue together
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> borne in <hi>Nycopin</hi> the 26 <hi>nouem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1593. and dyed the 25 of <hi>may</hi> 1594.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Guſtauus Adolphus</hi> King of the <hi>Suedes, Goths</hi> and <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>andales,</hi> great Prince in <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Duke in <hi>Eſthen</hi> and <hi>Carelia,</hi> Lord of <hi>Ingermanlande,</hi> &amp;c. was borne in the Kingly Palace of <hi>Stockholm</hi> the 9 of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> in the yeere 1594. He was crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the 12 of <hi>October</hi> 1617. He was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the 25 of <hi>October</hi> 1620. unto <hi>Marie Eleonora,</hi> daughter to <hi>Iohn Sigiſmund,</hi> Marqueſſe and Elector of <hi>Brandenburg.</hi>
                        <pb facs="tcp:23319:13"/>Shee was crowned Queene of <hi>Suede</hi> three daies after. Their iſſue
<list>
                           <item>1 A daughter borne dead the 24 <hi>Iuly</hi> in the yeere of Chriſt 1621.</item>
                           <item>2 <hi>Chriſtina</hi> the I. borne in <hi>October</hi> 1623, but died the next yeere fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</item>
                           <item>3 <hi>Chriſtina</hi> II. borne the 8 of <hi>Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1626 at <hi>Stockholm.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>3 <hi>Marie Elizabeth</hi> born the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> of <hi>March</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1596. in <hi>Orebrog,</hi> was mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the 29 of <hi>November</hi> 1612 vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Finlandt</hi> and <hi>Oſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gothland.</hi> She died in the yeere 1619 in <hi>Lyncopin</hi> and was buried there in the chiefe Church neere her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band.</item>
                           <item>4 <hi>Charles Phillip</hi> Duke in <hi>Suderman, Nericia</hi> and <hi>Verhmlandt, &amp;c.</hi> was borne the 23 of <hi>Aprill</hi> in <hi>anno</hi> 1600. He died the 25. of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1622. of
<pb facs="tcp:23319:13"/>a burning Fever in his returne to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Norcopin</hi> upon the frontiers of <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> after that his brother <hi>Gu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtavus Adolphus</hi> had taken <hi>Rugen</hi> the chiefe Citie in <hi>Leiflandt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>B</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> the firſt Sonne of <hi>Iohn</hi> the III. King of <hi>Suede</hi> and of the <hi>Goths,</hi> was borne at <hi>Gripſolm</hi> the 20 of <hi>Iune</hi> 1566. He was elected in <hi>Cracaw</hi> King of <hi>Polonia,</hi> of this name the III, <hi>December</hi> 27. in the yeere 1587. and the 20 of <hi>February</hi> 1594. Hee was alſo crowned King of <hi>Suede</hi> in <hi>Vpſalia,</hi> Hee married</p>
               <p>☞ <hi>Anna,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> Duke of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the 21 of <hi>May</hi> 1592. and was crowned Queene of <hi>Polonia</hi> the 31. of the ſaid <hi>May.</hi> She died the 31 of <hi>Ianua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> 1598. having had iſſue together
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Anna Maria,</hi> borne at <hi>Worſchaw</hi> the 23 of <hi>May</hi> 1593. and died the 9 of <hi>February</hi> 1600.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23319:14"/>
                     <item>2 <hi>Katherine</hi> I. borne at <hi>Stockholm</hi> the 9 of <hi>may,</hi> in the yeere 1594 and dyed al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there the 15 of <hi>iune,</hi> but buried in <hi>Cracaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Wladiſtaus Sigiſmund,</hi> Prince of <hi>Polonia,</hi> Adminiſtrator of the Dukedome of <hi>Seuerin</hi> and <hi>Zeruico,</hi> &amp;c. was born in <hi>Cracaw</hi> in the yeer of Chriſt 1595. the 9 of Iune.</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Katherine</hi> II. was borne at <hi>Worſaw</hi> the 17 of Septemb. in <hi>anno</hi> 1596. Shee died the 2 of Iune 1597.</item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> was taken alive out of his mothers belly, the ſame being cut, the higheſt neceſſity requiring it, the 2 of February 1598. preſently baptized, &amp; lived not full an houre after.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>☞</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> ſiſter of the full bloud to <hi>Aune</hi> the former wife, was by <hi>Paul</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:23319:14"/>fift Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> his diſpenſation marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the 9 of Decemb. in the yeere of Chriſt 1605. to the foreſaid <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> of <hi>Polonia,</hi> and had iſſue by her
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Iohn Caſimire</hi> I. borne in <hi>Cracaw</hi> the 25 of December 1607. he died the next yeere the 14 of Ianuary.</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Iohn Caſimire</hi> II. Prince of <hi>Polonia,</hi> &amp;c. was borne at <hi>Cracaw</hi> the 22 of March 1609.</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Iohn Albiet</hi> Prince of <hi>Polonia,</hi> &amp;c. was borne at <hi>Worſaw,</hi> the 25 of <hi>May.</hi> 1612.</item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Charles Ferdinand,</hi> Prince of <hi>Polonia,</hi> was borne the 13 of <hi>October,</hi> 1613, at <hi>Worſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 <hi>Alexander Charles,</hi> Prince of <hi>Polonia</hi> &amp;c. was borne the 4 of <hi>November,</hi> 1614, at <hi>Worſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:23319:15"/>
                     <item>6 <hi>Anna Constantia</hi> was borne the 26 of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1616 at <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>orſaw,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed 24 of <hi>May</hi> the ſame yeere.</item>
                     <item>7 <hi>Anna Katherine</hi> was borne the 17, of <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1619. at <hi>VVorſaw.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="genealogy">
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:15"/>
            <head>A SHORT GE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NEALOGICALL DEDVCTION OF THE <hi>PEDEGREE</hi> AND <hi>PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GENIE</hi> OF THE PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENT KINGS OF <hi>SVEDEN</hi> AND POLONIA.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>OHN the firſt of <hi>Oreby,</hi> Knigh, and Councellor of the Kingdome of <hi>Sueden,</hi> ſonne of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern</hi> the III. chiefe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour and Arch-ſewer of the ſaid Kingdome, and Nephew to <hi>Nicholas</hi> the II. of <hi>Biorne,</hi> Knight and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Stockholm</hi> under King <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:16"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Ericke</hi> I. of <hi>Gripſolm</hi> Kinght and Councellor of the Kingdom of <hi>Sueden,</hi> and governor in <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtiern,</hi> 4 of <hi>Oreby,</hi> Knight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anna,</hi> the wife of <hi>Iohn Turon,</hi> the Kings Marſhall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guſtauus</hi> I. Gouernor the firſt time of <hi>Sueden,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the yeere 1523. King of <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Gothland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Margaret</hi> firſt the wife of <hi>Peter Brahe,</hi> Earle of <hi>Wiſingburg,</hi> then the wife of <hi>Iohn</hi> Earle of <hi>Hoten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> and <hi>Oſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the yeere 1574.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:16"/>
            <p> Of <hi>Katherine</hi> Queene, the daughter of <hi>Magnus</hi> Duke of Lowe <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onte.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Erick</hi> 2. King of <hi>Sueden</hi> and <hi>Gothla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d,</hi> the 14 of this name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Guſtaus</hi> a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, who di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in <hi>Muſcouia</hi> after hee had lived a while in the Court of <hi>Rudolph</hi> II. Emperour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Syria,</hi> the wife of <hi>Hen. Toddens,</hi> Baron in <hi>Finland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Queen <hi>Margaret</hi> his kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman in bloud, the daugh ter of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holm</hi> Kn<hi rend="sup">ht</hi>. &amp; Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in <hi>Weſtgoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3. King of <hi>Sueden</hi> &amp; <hi>Gothland,</hi> Du. of <hi>Finland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Katherine</hi> wife <hi>Ezard</hi> 2. Earle of <hi>aſtfrie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlandt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Cecilia</hi> wife to <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:23319:17"/>
               <item>4 <hi>Magnus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Eaſtgoth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Anne,</hi> wife to <hi>George Iohn,</hi> Duke of <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zelſtein</hi> Count <hi>Palatine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Sophia,</hi> wife to <hi>Magnus</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, Duke of Low <hi>Saxonie.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> wife to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher</hi> Duke of <hi>Mechel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8 <hi>Charles,</hi> Duke firſt of <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landt, Sudermanlandt</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricia,</hi> choſen afterwards, <hi>viz. Anno</hi> 1600. King of <hi>Sueden, Gothland</hi> and <hi>Wandalia,</hi> and crowned <hi>ann.</hi> 1607. looke at the letter A.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Of Queene <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therine,</hi> the wife of <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> King of <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Sigiſmund,</hi> King of <hi>Polonia</hi> and <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Queene <hi>Gunill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> deſcended of ancient and principall Gentry in <hi>East-gothland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn,</hi> Duke of <hi>Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Eaſt-goth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:17"/>
            <p> Of Queene <hi>Anne</hi> Arch-dutcheſſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Anna Maria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Vladiſlaus Sigiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Katherine.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Chriſtopher.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Of Queene <hi>Conſtantia,</hi> Arch-dutcheſſe of <hi>Auſtria.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>Iohn Caſimire.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Iohn Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimire</hi> II. Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Iohn Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert</hi> Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4 <hi>Charles Ferdina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</hi> Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5 <hi>Alexander Charles</hi> Prince of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6 <hi>Anna Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantia.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7 <hi>Anna Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:23319:18"/>
               <head>A.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> 6. of this name, King of <hi>Sue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Gothland</hi> and <hi>Wandalia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Of <hi>Mary</hi> Counteſſe <hi>Palatine,</hi> daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to <hi>Ludowicke</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Margaret Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Elizabeth Sabina.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Lewis</hi> Duke of <hi>Sudermanland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Guſtavus</hi> 2. Duke of <hi>Sudermanland.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Marie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>Of the Dutcheſſe <hi>Chriſtina</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Adolph</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein</hi> neece to <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> 1 King of <hi>Denmarke</hi> and <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> Ki. of <hi>Sueden, Gothland,</hi> great Prince of <hi>Finland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Many Elizabeth</hi> wif to <hi>Iohn</hi> Duke of <hi>Finland</hi> &amp; <hi>Eaſtgothla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. Charles Philip</hi> Duk of <hi>Suder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manland, Nericia</hi> &amp; <hi>Vermla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chriſtina</hi> 1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chriſtina</hi> 2.</item>
               </list>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:18"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Dutch</hi> Copie of this Pedegree firſt penned and printed, where, and by whom (as thou ſeeſt) was ſent into <hi>England</hi> to a Perſon of note and qualitie, who being well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the advancement of the honor of Chriſtian Princes, thought it fit to be publiſhed, and therefore tranſlated it. Now it appeares by this Genealogie faithfully collected and ſet forth, that this moſt noble King of <hi>Sueden (Gustavus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolphus)</hi> is lineally deſcended not onely of <hi>Atavis Regibus,</hi> but of a Race of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and himſelfe the greateſt; for the
<pb facs="tcp:23319:19"/>
               <hi>German</hi> Churches groaning as loud, though not ſo long as the <hi>Iewes</hi> (who were delivered by <hi>Gedeon, Iephtah</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) have cauſe to call him ſo; howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Generall <hi>Tilly</hi> in his Letter to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty of <hi>Sueden</hi> termes him, (who is Gods anointed King) but
<note n="*" place="margin">In the <hi>Suediſh Intelligen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer pa.</hi> 121</note> 
               <hi>Cavalier;</hi> of whom that were much rather to bee uttered which <hi>Seneca</hi> relates one to have ſaid of <hi>Caeſar, Qui apud Caeſarem dicere audent, mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitudinem ejus ignorant, qui non audent, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitatem.</hi> God proſper the Perſon, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genie and proceedings of this Heroicall and religious Prince,
<note place="margin">Mutus ſit oportet qui non lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem. Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar.</note> to whole higheſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and happines my hearty deſires and prayers being devoted (as I truſt thine is) doe thus expreſſe themſelves in this ſhort <hi>Panegyrick.</hi> And ſo farewell.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:23319:19"/>
            <lg>
               <l>SPlendida quàm Generis ſeries ab origine prima</l>
               <l>Surgit, Suecorum qualis pertexitur Ordo,</l>
               <l>Maiorum patet hìc, Gentiſque Propago peroſae,</l>
               <l>Perſtrictam ſtellae Borealis lumine Romam.</l>
               <l>Eccè genus quantum in ſeros conferre Nepotes</l>
               <l>Et Proavi poſſunt, naſcenti affulſit Adolpho,</l>
               <l>Et quantum in Proavos poſſunt conferre Nepotes,</l>
               <l>Guſtavus parta Rex cum virtute rependit.</l>
               <l>Ignorant gentes genus illius; Anglus at Atlas,</l>
               <l>Quique bibit Tanaim, torrentis &amp; accola Gangis,</l>
               <l>Geſta ſcient eius praeclara, peric'la, labores,</l>
               <l>Quanta tulit fecitque pius pronomine Christi.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
